Guide to the Elisavietta Ritchie literary papers, 1947-2014 MS2333
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Elisavietta Ritchie literary papers
1947-2014
1970-1990
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ritchie, Elisavietta
MS2333
6.75 Linear Feet
Elisavietta (Lisa) Ritchie's fiction, poetry, creative non-fiction, photographs, and translations from Russian and French have appeared in numerous publications. This collection includes various drafts and publications of poems and stories written by Ritchie. It also contains correspondence to and from Ritchie, including letters from her parents and correspondence written in Russian. The collection dates from 1964-2014.
Collection Scope and Contents
This collection contains literary papers related to the life and career of writer Elisavietta Ritchie. This includes various drafts and publications of poems and stories, as well as a few items of publicity. It also includes correspondence with her parents, George L. Artamoff and Jessie B. Downing, and letters in Russian. The collection dates from 1964-2014.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Elisavietta (Lisa) Richie's fiction, poetry, creative non-fiction, photographs, and translations from Russian and French have appeared in numerous publications and have won various awards. Ritchie has read at the Library of Congress, Harbourfront, Folger Library, Pittsburgh International Forum, many libraries, universities, schools and other cultural centers in the United States, Canada, Australia, Russia, and under the auspices of the United States Information Agency, in Brazil, around the Far East, and the Balkans. She often teaches writing workshops for adults and children, and occasionally lectures to teachers on the poetry-in-the-school program.
She founded The Wineberry Press, and for three years was president of Washington Writer's Publishing House. Books edited include The Dolphin's Arc: Poems on Endangered Creatures of the Sea. Her photographs have appeared in The New York Times etc.
Collection Organization
Organized into 3 series: Literary writings, Correspondence and Publications.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elisavietta Ritchie, 19 October 2014 [2014.037]. A second smaller donation was made in 2017 (Accession 2017.043)
Poetry -- 20th century; Poetry -- 21st century; Poetry; Ritchie, Elisavietta
- Literary writings, 1964-2014; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes various drafts and publications of poems and stories written by Elisavietta Ritchie. It also contains a few items of publicity material. It dates from 1964-2014.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - "A Sheath of Dreams" and "Other Games" - Protens Press 1976, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "An Electric Train, for a Girl?", December 2013; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Arc of the Storm" - Drafts and Galleys (1/2), 1998; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Arc of the Storm" - Drafts and Galleys (2/2), 1998; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Arc of the Storm" - Final Galley including Reviews (1/2), 1998; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "The Arc of the Storm" - Final Galley including Reviews (2/2), 1998; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "At the Antipodes" (1/2), c. 1995; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "At the Antipodes" (2/2), c. 1995; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Barbie of the Bee-Port", 2005; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Because of Two Ubangi Butterflies", 1974; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Breaking Formation", n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Breaking Formation" and "A Russian Legacy", 1980s and 1990s; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "The Caldecott Cycles", n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Caldecott Cycles", 2010; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Christian Science Monitor - Drafts and Publications (1/3), 1978-1985; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Christian Science Monitor - Drafts and Publications (2/3), 1978-1985; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Christian Science Monitor - Drafts and Publications (3/3), 1978-1985; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Diary from Working in a Nursing Home", 1978-1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Drafts of Stories and Poems - All published (1/2), 1988-1989; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Drafts of Stories and Poems - All published (2/2), 1988-1989; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Early Drafts, Library of Congress Readings, etc., 1989-1990; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Elegy for the Other Woman", 1982; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Essays and Speeches, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Flying Time" (1/2), 1978-1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Flying Time" (2/2), 1978-1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Glad I Gave to Art My All: From the Artist's Bedside", 1970-2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Group of 4 Poems, 2014; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Handwritten Notes and Drafts, 1966-1988; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Here, Even the Blue Crabs Compose", 2000; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Hosiah and Mike and Sukie with Her Damned Watermelon" (1/2), 2014; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Hosiah and Mike and Sukie with Her Damned Watermelon" (2/2), 2014; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Hunters and Cleaners", late 1980s-early 1990s; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Journal Pieces - Drafts, 1979-1982; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Lions in the Wings" Collection - Various Drafts, 2013-2014; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Material for a Display at Calvert Library, 2010; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Publications - NY Times, Washington Post, Gnostica News, 1969-1985; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Stories, 1973-1985; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Poems and Stories - Titles A thru G, 1968-2014; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Poems and Stories - Titles H thru M, 1968-2014; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Poems and Stories - Titles N thru S, 1968-2014; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Poems and Stories - Titles T thru Z, 1968-2014; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Publications in Newspapers and Journals (1/2), 1973-2014; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Publications in Newspapers and Journals (2/2), 1973-2014; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Publicity - Flyer and Program, 2013-2014; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Published Poems and Stories, 1964-2014; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Raking the Snow" - also includes peoms from "Balkan October", 1983; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Raking the Snow" and "A Balkan October" (1/2), 1981; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Raking the Snow" and "A Balkan October" (2/2), 1981; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Raking the Snow" -subsequent Rewrites of Poems, 2013; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Read USA Roundtables and PR, 1973-1989; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Reviews, 1983; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Rework and Drafts - Some Published, 1988-1989; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Rewrite and Submit, 2001-2011; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "The Scotch Runner", 2013; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Tiger Upstairs on Connecticut Avenue" (1/3), 2012-2013; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "Tiger Upstairs on Connecticut Avenue" (2/3), 2012-2013; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "Tiger Upstairs on Connecticut Avenue" (3/3), 2012-2013; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Translations, 1969; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Tracking Skulls" - Drafts of Poems, 2003-2011; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "The Ultimate Susan Story", n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Unmarked Manuscript, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Untitled Manuscript, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Untitled Pieces, n.d., undated; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "Updating the Addressbook - Poems of Various Eras on Bereavement", 2010-2013; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Various Poems, 2006-2008; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1964-2013; Series 2
  This series includes correspondence both to and from Elisavietta Ritchie. It contains a number of letters from her parents George L. Artamoff and Jessie B. Downing, as well as letters in Russian. It dates from 1964-2013.
  - Correspondence from Parents - George L. Artamoff and Jessie B. Downing (1/2), 1966-1967; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from Parents - George L. Artamoff and Jessie B. Downing (2/2), 1966-1967; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence in Russian, 1964-1970; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1965-2013; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Publications, 1947-2007; Series 3
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains publications collected by Elisavietta Ritchie between 1947-2007.
  - Publications, 1947-1962; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Publications, 1968-1969; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Publications, 1970-1978; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Publications, 1981-1984; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Publications, 1986-1989; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Publications, 1989-1989; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Publications, 1990-1999; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Publications, 2000-2007; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - John Pauker, 1978-1991; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)